<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>paws on Dyfan Jones Brain Dump HQ</title>
    <link>/tags/paws/</link>
    <description>Recent content in paws on Dyfan Jones Brain Dump HQ</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-uk</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 29 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
        <atom:link href="/tags/paws/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>An Amazon SDK for R!?</title>
      <link>/post/an-amazon-sdk-for-r/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/an-amazon-sdk-for-r/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.r-bloggers.com&#34;&gt;RBloggers&lt;/a&gt;|&lt;a href=&#34;http://feeds.feedburner.com/RBloggers&#34;&gt;RBloggers-feedburner&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;intro&#34;&gt;Intro:&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a long time I have found it difficult to leverage the benefits of cloud computer in my R model builds. This was mainly down to the initial lack of understanding of cloud compute and the setting up of R on cloud computer environments. When I noticed that AWS was bringing out a new product &lt;a href=&#34;https://aws.amazon.com/sagemaker/&#34;&gt;AWS Sagemaker&lt;/a&gt;, the possiblities of what it could provide seemed like a dream come true.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Amazon SageMaker provides every developer and data scientist with the ability to build, train, and deploy machine learning models quickly. Amazon SageMaker is a fully-managed service that covers the entire machine learning workflow to label and prepare your data, choose an algorithm, train the model, tune and optimize it for deployment, make predictions, and take action. Your models get to production faster with much less effort and lower cost. (&lt;a href=&#34;https://aws.amazon.com/sagemaker/&#34;&gt;https://aws.amazon.com/sagemaker/&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A question about AWS Sagemake came to mind: &lt;em&gt;Does it work for R developers???&lt;/em&gt; Well&amp;hellip;not exactly. True it provides a simple way set up an R environment in the cloud but it doesn&amp;rsquo;t give the means to access other AWS products for example &lt;a href=&#34;https://aws.amazon.com/s3/&#34;&gt;AWS S3&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://aws.amazon.com/athena/&#34;&gt;AWS Athena&lt;/a&gt; out of the box. However for Python this is not a problem. Amazon has provided a SDK for Python called &lt;a href=&#34;https://boto3.amazonaws.com/v1/documentation/api/latest/index.html&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;boto3&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, which comes pre-installed on AWS Sagemaker.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It isn&amp;rsquo;t all bad news, RStudio has developed a package called &lt;a href=&#34;https://rstudio.github.io/reticulate/&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;reticulate&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; that lets R interfaced into Python. So using &lt;code&gt;reticulate&lt;/code&gt; in combination with &lt;code&gt;boto3&lt;/code&gt; gives R full access to all of AWS products from Sagemaker similar to Python. However are there any other methods for R user to connect to AWS?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;aws-interfaces-for-r&#34;&gt;AWS interfaces for R:&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;paws-https-paws-r-github-io-an-r-sdk&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://paws-r.github.io/&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;paws&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; an R SDK:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Paws is a Package for Amazon Web Services in R. Paws provides access to the full suite of AWS services from within R.(&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/paws-r/paws&#34;&gt;https://github.com/paws-r/paws&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I want to programatically connect to AWS I would resort to Python. AWS&amp;rsquo;s &lt;code&gt;boto3&lt;/code&gt; is an excellent means to connect to AWS and leverage it&amp;rsquo;s functionality. However R now has it&amp;rsquo;s own SDK, into AWS. This came as a little surprise to me as I started to accept that R might never have an SDK for AWS how wrong I was.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What particularly shocked me was how well developed and easy the package was. It felt natural to switch between Python&amp;rsquo;s &lt;code&gt;boto3&lt;/code&gt; and R&amp;rsquo;s &lt;code&gt;paws&lt;/code&gt;. Almost like it was a long lost brother.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Here is a quick example to show the comparison between &lt;code&gt;boto3&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;paws&lt;/code&gt;. Returning a list of all objects in S3 inside a prefix:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Python&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;import boto3

s3 = boto3.Session().client(&amp;quot;s3&amp;quot;)
obj = s3.list_objects(Bucket = &#39;mybucket&#39;, Prefix = &amp;quot;prefix_1/&amp;quot;)
[x.get(&amp;quot;Key&amp;quot;) for x in obj.get(&amp;quot;Contents&amp;quot;)]

&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;R&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;s3 &amp;lt;- paws::s3()

obj &amp;lt;- s3$list_objects(Bucket = &#39;mybucket&#39;, Prefix = &amp;quot;prefix_1/&amp;quot;)
lapply(obj$Contents, function(x) x$Key)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From this quick example it is clear that the &lt;code&gt;paws&lt;/code&gt; SDK&amp;rsquo;s syntax is extremely similar to &lt;code&gt;boto3&lt;/code&gt;, although with an R twist. But this is only a good thing, as hundreds of people know the &lt;code&gt;boto3&lt;/code&gt; already and therefore they will be familiar with &lt;code&gt;paws&lt;/code&gt; by association. I can&amp;rsquo;t express the potential for R users now they have a SDK into AWS. A good project that utilises the &lt;code&gt;paws&lt;/code&gt; sdk is the package &lt;a href=&#34;https://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/noctua/index.html&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;noctua&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;code&gt;noctua&lt;/code&gt; creates a wrapper of the &lt;code&gt;paws&lt;/code&gt; connection to AWS Athena and developes a &lt;code&gt;DBI&lt;/code&gt; interface for R users. We will go into the package &lt;code&gt;noctua&lt;/code&gt; in the next blog. First here is the example how to work with AWS Athena when using &lt;code&gt;paws&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Submit a query to Athena using &lt;code&gt;paws&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;# create an AWS Athena object
athena &amp;lt;- paws::athena()

# Submit query to AWS Athena
res &amp;lt;- athena$start_query_execution(
            QueryString = &amp;quot;show Databases&amp;quot;,
            ResultConfiguration = 
                list(OutputLocation = &amp;quot;s3://mybucket/queries/&amp;quot;))

# Get Status of query
result &amp;lt;- get_query_execution(QueryExecutionId = res$QueryExecutionId)

# Return results if query is successful
if(result$QueryExecution$Status$State == &amp;quot;FAILED&amp;quot;) {
  stop(result$QueryExecution$Status$StateChangeReason, call. = FALSE)
} else {output &amp;lt;- 
          athena$get_query_results(
              QueryExecutionId = res$QueryExecutionId,
              MaxResults = 1)}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From initial view it might look daunting however this is exactly the same interface that &lt;code&gt;boto3&lt;/code&gt; provides when working with AWS Athena. The good news is that &lt;code&gt;noctua&lt;/code&gt; wraps all of this and creates the DBI method &lt;code&gt;dbGetQuery&lt;/code&gt; for &lt;code&gt;paws&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;paws&lt;/code&gt; is an excellent R SDK into AWS, so please download &lt;code&gt;paws&lt;/code&gt; and give it ago, I am sure you will be pleasantly surprised like myself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;install.packages(&amp;quot;paws&amp;quot;)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note:&lt;/strong&gt; For more examples, the developers of &lt;code&gt;paws&lt;/code&gt; have created some code examples &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/paws-r/paws/tree/master/examples&#34;&gt;https://github.com/paws-r/paws/tree/master/examples&lt;/a&gt; and a  documentation website &lt;a href=&#34;https://paws-r.github.io/&#34;&gt;https://paws-r.github.io/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;botor-https-daroczig-github-io-botor&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://daroczig.github.io/botor/&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;botor&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; :&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This R package provides raw access to the ‘Amazon Web Services’ (‘AWS’) ‘SDK’ via the ‘boto3’ Python module and some convenient helper functions (currently for S3 and KMS) and workarounds, eg taking care of spawning new resources in forked R processes. (&lt;a href=&#34;https://daroczig.github.io/botor/&#34;&gt;https://daroczig.github.io/botor/&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When using &lt;code&gt;botor&lt;/code&gt; on AWS Sagemaker, R users can easily interact with all of AWS products in the exact same manner as a Python user. However &lt;code&gt;botor&lt;/code&gt;&amp;rsquo;s convenient helper functions certainly do make the exeperience working on sagemaker. Here is a quick example to demostrate how easy/ useful these helper function are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Upload iris data.frame to s3 bucket&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;library(botor)

write_s3(iris, data.table::fwrite, &amp;quot;s3://mybucket/iris.csv&amp;quot;)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Read s3 file back into R as a data.frame&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;read_s3(&amp;quot;s3:://mybucket/iris.csv&amp;quot;, data.table::fread)

&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These convenient helper functions are not limited to just reading/writing data in csv format. They can also be used to upload R models, which can be really useful when wanted to store pre-built models. Here is a quick example of what I like to call a &lt;em&gt;crap&lt;/em&gt; model.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;train &amp;lt;- iris[1:20,1:4]
test &amp;lt;- iris[21:40,1:4]
 
model &amp;lt;- lm(Petal.Width ~., train)

&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Uploading and downloading R models to S3&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;s3_write(model, saveRDS, &amp;quot;s3://mybucket/crap_model.RDS&amp;quot;)
s3_model &amp;lt;- s3_read(&amp;quot;s3://mybucket/crap_model.RDS&amp;quot;, readRDS)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is really clear to see how useful &lt;code&gt;botor&lt;/code&gt; is when working in AWS.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;cloudyr-project&#34;&gt;Cloudyr Project:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I personally havent used the AWS cloudyr packages, however I don&amp;rsquo;t want to leave them out. The &lt;a href=&#34;https://cloudyr.github.io/&#34;&gt;cloudyr project&lt;/a&gt; aim is to bring R onto the cloud compute:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The goal of this initiative is to make cloud computing with R easier, starting with robust tools for working with cloud computing platforms.(&lt;a href=&#34;https://cloudyr.github.io/&#34;&gt;https://cloudyr.github.io/&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please go to the cloudyr github &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/cloudyr&#34;&gt;https://github.com/cloudyr&lt;/a&gt; as alot of work has gone into making R easier to work with cloud computing. They have alot of documentation plus they are actively developing R packages to make user experience better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary:&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe that all of these packages are critical if you wish to work in AWS when using R. &lt;code&gt;paws&lt;/code&gt; certainly give a R feel utilising AWS products. &lt;code&gt;botor&lt;/code&gt; helper functions make the experience very easily and helpful. Personally I would love Amazon to include these package in Sagemaker. Without them Sagemaker becomes near impossible to work with,  R users.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
      
                  <category>R</category>
      
                  <category>paws</category>
      
                  <category>Boto3</category>
      
                  <category>Python</category>
      
      
            <category>RBloggers</category>
      
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>